hello it is January 25th 2023
and we are in covert 2 of the par at all
textbook Rune meeting 13.
today we are going to
jump back in start our seconds interval
of activities
there are a few ways we can go we can
just review structural aspects of Dakota
and accommodate anyone's like
suggestions or notes on some things that
could be interesting to develop with in
this one or an aside little sandbox
then we will look to the textbook itself
and we will look at
where the first five chapters
got us
and where we're going with the second
half of the book which has a different
Form and Function then the first half of
the book
so first off anyone want to just
adony
General comment how now that it's 2023
where are they in their Active Learning
and application Journey
how is our Niche similar or different
than it was
in September
through November when we worked through
the first five chapters
any thoughts or or we can continue on
just want to
leave that space
okay
feel free to raise your hand or just
unmute or put in the chat or anything
like that
um
broadly
the layout
is the similar
textbook group overview has information
on our live meetings
and
um
that's where you can download the
textbook
the textbook section itself
contains different types of things that
are in the textbook such as the
equations
which have all been brought out with
images and page at least
but there's a lot of improvements that
we could make to the descriptions and
the tagging
similarly with figures we have all
figures brought out
but there's a lot of contributions that
can be made
to um descriptions and tagging
boxes and tables
similar
code implementations
we
um I'll add a link to block prints so if
anybody
um
which is what we've one thing that we've
worked on last few months we have about
uh 40 or 50 implementations of active
in Python C plus plus Julia Matlab
so
um accessible from here
um and we can for those who want to
start
um getting more into the code
and I'll just show one more piece that
we worked on earlier today in the block
fronts meeting
in model stream 7.2
um
a notebook was used
in epistemic contextual multi-armed
Bandit simulation was provided by Connor
Heights
um just works perfectly no no tweaking
is needed
uses octave Loop defines Etc
and what we did today was we took the
active ontology
and we then said how is this set up in
the contextual Bandit how do they set up
B okay here are here's how B is set up
one can click this
and then in a plain text
paste in the whole script
so
this is not the only way that we're
going to be
working towards modeling but as the
second half of the textbook is about
building a generative model in the
process the recipe
we have like
multiple functions in this cohort too as
we go through
chapter six or ten
one
function will be to
to the extent that we want to develop
our own
generative model and simulation
just didactically just to have something
that we increment along to help us
understand
or if there's some outcome that people
want to pursue
research or application oriented like
second half of the textbook is
um the time to do it and
even relative to last September we have
significantly better tools
so there's totally an approach to go
from a natural language understanding
of these ontology terms
two
how to do it in pi mdp
and it's pretty reasonable that somebody
who wants to pursue this direction we
could just add another column copy it
over make the tweak and there's a few
other
pieces but a lot of that is going to
come up in chapter six
um in chapter notes and questions we
have the chapters themselves
and a detailed table of contents
and then each chapter has subset view of
the questions so if you have a question
within a given chapter
or you want to help improve and curate
the discourse
please just like add a row
in the questions section or just make
improvements to the answers and
discourse
um
so we'll um
continue to work with questions as well
as whatever notes people add uh
to just whatever anything else they want
to highlight
um into the more discourse sections
here's the home of the questions table
but it's shown in the chapters as well
um ideas and insights people are always
welcome to add just sort of
nuggets or summaries
for what
they're updating their models with what
they're coming away from from these
sections
math learning group has no
current
um live activities but there's a huge
amount of
uh resources and and some summaries that
are written
but there's always
many things for people to do with
testing out math learning
um
project ideas
we can return to but that's kind of
where we left off with in the last
meeting
of the first half
um future textbook groups we organized
that
at the end of last interval but as
always if people are having like
thoughts or they want to
give
comments or have ideas for
just it can provide the feedback here
directly or
um other notes
and Errata which have been shared with
the authors
I'll also note that um on
J February 27th
Thomas Parr is going to join for a live
stream
so if anyone is um
oh let me just check the UTC time right
now
but if anybody wants to it'll be
17 UTC
on February 27th
so it'll be in Zoom just like this
um
and
we have one month before then
to
prepare
some
questions that we want to highlight and
ask
so
um
those are just some overview Coda
elements and some updates that have
happened in the broader
modeling space over the last few weeks
and months
any
just general or comments on that
is
a
um over a paper or is it going to be
over the textbook or is he just joining
to the question or what is the subject
matter
it's this textbook also your audio is
very off
but yes this textbook
okay any other
daughter questions or we'll turn to look
at the
book
okay
well anyone who has been in cohort one
or otherwise how would they characterize
chapters one through five
as opposed to Chapters six through ten
is any better no not at all okay then I
won't
okay just you can type it or just add it
in the coda
um Ali go for it as anyone else
I think uh chapter one through five was
um basically for a building the the
requisite fundamentals for uh designing
and maybe
uh
applying those Concepts in a much more
a practical way to some real world
situations that we deal we'll deal with
in the second part of the book second
half of the book uh but uh in my opinion
uh even more than this dichotomy between
the fundamentals or application oriented
approaches between the second between
the two halves of the book uh the very
structure of those chapters I mean the
pedagogical structures of those chapters
are very different because uh as much as
in the first chapter we're dealing with
some general
propositions and some general structures
and Frameworks in order to frame the
theory in a comprehensive and
a kind of uh
layered structure in the second half of
the book we're much more in a case of
study based approach and we're dealing
with uh some uh solved examples so to
speak and in some other cases even some
open questions that we can uh we can try
our hands on later
after well learning the basic
fundamental approach to solving these
kind of problems in active inference
framework but in my opinion those these
two
halves of the book are can can even be
uh seen as two separate books uh because
of their uh fundamental differences in
in every aspect
very interesting thank you
anyone else just what are your thoughts
how have chapters one through five sat
with you now that you've
read it and digested it
and then if you have looked at six
through ten
how would you contrast it with chapters
one through five and then we'll look
more in fine grain
I would say one two five was like the
blanket
and six through ten is like the hidden
States
ah
a
awesome
keep the keep the octane fontology 100
percent
a great metaphor
yep
observations one through five
observations six or ten hidden State
inference
Neil
yeah so the first half I I didn't get as
much out of it as I would like to have
it's it's still very mathematical
um but that maths didn't really lead to
insights
um I've I've gone ahead and had a look
through chapters seven
uh and eight
and they look uh
well a lot more like their applications
that I I get I seem to be getting more
from that
than
so that's that's looking good
thank you yes some sometimes it helps to
do the the applications before the
theory
um to give you some sort of Direction
yes
anyone else want to add a comment or all
add a general comment on the chapters
and then we'll go to the subsections and
so on
uh Ali
I also agree with Neil that maybe some
of uh the contents of the second half of
the book uh might work better if they
were interspersed with the material from
the first chapter uh to uh have a much
more goal-oriented vision in mind or and
to not lose the big picture
uh for the coming chapters
yeah
we have with a lot to
infer and do with the pedagogical
ordering and respecting all different
learning preferences and paths
um
we're going to be heading into chapter
six in the coming
um two weeks in our cohort
and here's from the summary of chapter
six
um in this chapter
they're outlining design choices and
they provide a four-step recipe
which we're going to spend a lot of time
working on because like that is our
you know we're all Sous chefs in the
kitchen this is our recipe structure
that every single time a sous chef gives
their input on how to improve it or how
to make something that's a little bit
tacit or implicit into a
checklist
or a template or an automation every
time a sous chef sees that opportunity
the recipe gets better
um this sets up the remainder of the
book which is again what we're going to
be working through in the next three
months putting these ideas into practice
through illustrative examples
which ali
um referred to as like solved examples
and basically they are they might be
trivially solved but whereas what we saw
in terms of solved examples in chapters
one through five was like the frog
jumping out of the hand which is kind of
a solved example of Bayesian inference
now we're going to see some solved
examples
of the type
the active inference models are like
with a partially observable Markov
decision process
in the second half of the book is
designed to showcase the theoretical
principles presented in the first half
of the book
so let's look back to the first chapters
and then see how that is going to be
showcased
chapter one is like an introduction and
on the other side of the bookshelf
chapter 10 is going to be like a summary
recap so that's kind of like the opening
and the closing
bookmarks
um
chapter 2 and 3 cover the low road and
the high road to active inference we're
not going to uh or don't need to go into
it in a lot of detail right now but
those are the two paths that are laid
out to get two active inference
and chapter four puts us squarely in
active inference with a focus on what is
at the heart of active inference
modeling which are generative models
chapter 5 then focuses on one of the
areas where active inference models have
been most applied and applicable which
is in neurobiology and so chapter five
looks at several neurobiological systems
in detail
and how active inference is applied and
then has some tables that show more
broadly where those models have been
applied
so introduction
on what the book is about and its
overall Framing and structure
the two roads to active inference
from the mechanistic and the Bayesian in
the low road
and from the imperative for survival and
the free energy principle on the high
road
chapter 4 describing the structure of
the essence of what this kind of
modeling entails at least in the style
as the authors are laying it out
and then
immediately jumping into examples and
somewhat of a literature review overview
on some of the systems where it's been
most applied
that
are the theoretical principles presented
in the first half of the book
low road High Road
what the model is itself
and how we see it applied in
neurobiology
in the second half of the book
chapter six is going to start us off
with a recipe
and um
this question what are the four steps
previously we had a lot of good
discussion on these and a few other
questions so improving the discourse as
always adding questions
is super helpful
just
checking people's understanding checking
your own understanding
everyone adding one question per week
would result in
a quantity and quality of questions that
would be transformative truly one
question per week even if it seems
trivial or it's a speculative question
so questions are huge and in chapter six
we're focusing on this four-step recipe
it's about how to design active
inference models and
we'll have a lot of space and time
to connect it to
The Cutting Edge work in pi mdp
and approaches that we're using
with the active inference ontology
so that we can have a pathway from a
natural language understanding
of a given system of Interest
on through the kind of state space
representations that are required for pi
mdp so that's what chapter 6 is about
the recipe and the structure as the
authors are laying it out
and also keeping in mind
um not sure exactly which um moment this
was said but the audience for this
textbook I believe Carl said
the audience is something like a
master's students in computational
Psychiatry looking to apply this to
their own research
so
that is like
squarely what this chapter is oriented
to
after
um again all he said like chapters one
through five were about building those
requisite fundamentals
all right
then chapter seven and eight kind of
like the cousins of two and three are
gonna present
uh
duality
or some other kind of minimum two system
chapter seven is gonna look at acronym
in discrete time d a i discrete active
inference which is often affiliated with
decision making cognition
and then
chapter 8 is going to present active
inference in continuous time also
sometimes called m a i or motor active
inference because it can be and has been
used to describe continuous motor reflex
and actuation processes like joints and
movements
so there's many
flavors and variants of active inference
every time we see like an adjective
active inference deep affective
sophisticated
branching time all of these flavors and
adjectives
there's a whole growing Zoo
Wildlife Preserve but one of the most
important and also didactic differences
amongst active inference models are
their treatment of time
along the lines of many other simulation
approaches the difference between
discrete time and continuous time where
the discrete time is more like taking a
sum over finite sets and the continuous
time is a lot more like doing calculus
in chapter 9
knowing what we now know about how
active models can be
cooked up
and about two major classes of
generative models discrete and
continuous time
we'll look at model based data analysis
so
um
I'll just show one figure to um
highlight here's figure 7.1 so
we have a prior hidden States s b is how
the hidden States change their time a is
the mapping between hidden States and
observations
this relationship between the hidden
States and observations
is sometimes called the tale of two
densities
um
just Loosely slash poetically
because this a matrix
can be used to take a hidden state
and generate data What observations
would we expect
given the hidden State and a or you can
take observations and through a do
inference on hidden States
that is using a generative model
in its generative capacity
which is from the hidden states to
generate observations or in its
recognition density from empirical data
back to Hidden State inference of
unobservables
so in chapter 9
um that type of data based uh modeling
is described
whereas in the previous examples
uh things were more oriented towards
like just what is the structure of the
generative model
chapter 9 is going to bring us to
confront this question of with empirical
data
how can we then do state inference which
is a task that starts to look a lot more
like what day-to-day research and
Analysis looks like
and then
quickly as we begun
chapter 10.
is an overview
summarizes the structure of the book
again
gives a quick recap of each section
and provide some closing articulations
and next steps
so again they've laid out the book
broadly into sections
the first half gets as quickly as one
can two the heart
of active inference modeling the
generative model
then reminds us of some of the central
applications over the previous years in
neurobiology also using that as an
opportunity to discuss message passing
which doesn't
centrally feature but is something that
one can imagine will be developed more
then
chapter six or ten what we're going to
be focusing on in this second interval
of activity for cohort 2
we're going to start with a math free
chapter
where we um
are just looking at this recipe
that they're going to lay out which
it's going to be just super exciting
discussions
and there's a lot that
[Music]
um
everyone will be able to contribute on
this
because we'll be able to
come to a lot of
intersubjective clarity about how they
are laying out
the modeling approach
in active inference again according to
par Zulu and friston
and also use that as a starting point
for
specifying what they've proposed
asking questions that aren't addressed
in these short texts
and then connecting to our experience
with modeling whether we've used
programming languages or data analysis
or indifference disciplines and settings
all right so I was just giving a little
overview on the chapters and the
sections anyone have any comments you'd
like to add
on structure
or chapters M Carl
yeah um
I have a question I'm not so sure
whether this uh
is a little bit off but if you're so bad
show this this model this hidden Markov
model that you just showed with the
hidden States and and the observations
I am wondering so so I I would like
maybe I can just say this briefly you
already read to
what my research is about uh Daniel I
think you know so so I have a no I can't
I may have but please feel free just for
everyone's context whatever you like to
add go for it okay so so I have a huge
amount of data and I'm wondering whether
this um so behavioral data actually and
I was wondering whether this could be
the right approach to model this and my
question here is so the Matrix is a and
b are I guess independent
and so if there is a decision on this
hidden States as s
and the emission of the observation
through an a matrix
this is um somehow independent from the
successive State observation right so I
or is it or is there a possibility to
to
tell the system that the success so that
the emission of one observation from a
state
depends a little bit or the successive
State depends on what the previous state
has emitted what observation was
produced
I understand my question so it looks
like
uh the the transitions are independent
from the emissions and I'm not so sure
uh what this actually implies in the
modeling of my data
um does that question make sense
awesome thank you so there's a few
pieces
anyone want to give a first thought and
then this is like again it's an example
of what we can
add as a question you don't have to go
and tag everything with the active
fontology if you want but certainly one
could because you use a lot of active
ontology terms
but
regardless of how fully formed or
appropriate one thinks like adding the
question to these tables
is one of the most helpful ways that
those insights that we do want to share
in this space can have like
extremely highly leveraged impact even
without large language models being
trained on these documents which will
surely happen
these are important questions
so I'm just going to try to take notes
as people discuss this
on this questions and topics page so
Giuseppe and anyone else
so if I can answer my own question or a
thought at least
so one could add at the output a kind of
a language model
um or maybe and I don't know are there
are there such tweaks that are
um possible in this whole model
so if we if we say that the one
observation does not only depend on the
state which has emitted it but also on
the previous observation
how can we model I mean one way to model
this would be to have a language model
that runs over the over maybe
um
alternative possible observations and
then decide which
chain of sequence of observations one
has the highest likelihood this is
or how could some something like this be
modeled is this uh
is this taken account to uh in some ways
yeah great questions Giuseppe then Neil
than anyone else
I don't hear you Giuseppe
um yes I do
okay uh so I was thinking although the
the transition in my understanding the
transition matrices are pre-specified
then
at the at the moment of learning in a
sense
the the matrices are updated so to
reflect
the observations
so but but they're not immediately I
guess and they're not immediately
updated on the basis of the last
observation is that
is that correct
yeah I'll just briefly directly respond
in the simplest possible framing of this
partially observable Markov decision
process there's no learning or parameter
updating at all A and B are fixed
however we're in the Bayesian statistics
World we're in the Bayes area so
everything can be learnable
for example in this Pi mdp script first
there was an active inference Loop
specified and then the kind of cousin
function was specified where the B
Matrix was learnable
so one can have every variable here
fixed or learnable
it just depends how you actually do the
modeling and that's again what chapter 6
is going to confront us with
one can imagine that if you have a fixed
a matrix all you have to do is specify
the a matrix if you want to have
learning
the state space and the dimensionality
of your model has vastly increased
so that may be worth it in certain
situations
but now you're dealing with Decay rates
and
learning constants and critical
forgetting and just there's all these
features that you're just not dealing
with with the more reduced fixed model
so
all the parameters can be fixed or not
okay and then was there a second aspect
or on to Neil
yeah thank you
[Music]
okay my so I'm not
really I don't really understand this
but my
feeling is if if a and b are
interdependent does that mean that it's
not a matter of decision process
uh and if you've got a system where it's
where the current state is not just
dependent on the previous state but on
on the States before that then that's
that's not a a mark of
process
awesome yes that was the the
Direction I was going to add so from a
pure empirical perspective
the observations may have a strong
correlation so if you did a descriptive
statistical approach like
arima or just time series modeling you'd
find that like
there was a statistical correlation
amongst similar observations again we're
just thinking of some
you know temperature in a room hidden
State thermometer readings and the
observations there's some like time
autocorrelation
what the markovian property is even the
last names aren't informative this is
just what is called a markovian property
is that the presence is a Markov blanket
between the past and the future
in other words this is a map this isn't
the territory this is a map that helps
us reduce the dimensionality of all
possible models by considering those
that have this one very important
simplifying feature
which is that the past only influences
the future through the present
so yes observations might be the same
across different time points or they
might be correlated from a Time series
perspective
but architecturally
from the Bayesian graph model that we're
going to use
the way that we're going to model
those observations through a Time
is by having the observations
emitted or received
Tale of Two densities
by a hidden state which undergoes time
evolution
so there's no direct Edge between the
observation at T minus 1 and the
observation at T
the a matrix could be the same if it's a
fixed a or the a matrix may have even
changed if it's learnable a
but the key feature that makes this
partially observable
is the fact that some parts of the model
are observable like data observations
and some parts are not observable hidden
States so that's the partially
observable po part
and then what makes it a Markov process
is this present acting as the blanket
between the past and the future
and then what makes it a decision
process
is that we're inter this is just a
partially observable Markov process
in figure 7.1
partially observable hidden State
observations markovian property current
moments interleaving between the past
and the future
what makes it a Markov decision process
is that it has the markovian property
and
we are embedding action
into the Markov process how by having
evaluation
of alternative policies
and how they intervene
at the B Matrix
so that's why this is a partially
observable Markov decision process it
has all of those attributes
and there's justifications for why we
want it to be partially observable why
we want it to be markovian and why we
want it to be a decision process
and if somebody has some other modeling
scenario in mind
then
some of those adjectives might have to
change or you might add
adjectives
um
Ali and then anyone else
uh yes adding to which what you just
explained even when uh defining the B
Matrix uh we just add the indices based
on the state factors that are
controllable that are controllable or
um
because in that case uh with each action
the B Matrix would be different so this
means that we would need an index
specifying which action is actually
taken but for other contextual states
which are not in the under the control
of the agent we don't need any
additional
a transition probabilities for each
action so yeah even in defining the
structure of the B Matrix we distinguish
between the states that are controllable
and the contextual states that are out
of the control of the agents
awesome thank you yeah and and as we go
through chapter six in the coming two
weeks
which is a qualitative chapter
and then also look towards exactly how
these are set up in pi mdp
like this is a movement up down left
right or this is just a Left Right
movement or stay
these
affordances and transition probabilities
and everything like that
they get encoded in matrices
and these operations are like linear
algebra
like arrays or tensors or matrices
kind of
being collided with each other
the circles and the squares are
variables they're variables of slightly
different types but they are all
variables
and then the edges reflect like which
we're going to combine
and so each given variable
has a semantics
which we associate with an active
inference ontology term
D prior s hidden State a ambiguity
Matrix
oh observations B transition Matrix
Pi policy
policy is just the set of possible
actions that are evaluated by the agent
e is used for affordances
which is like the action possibilities
in one moment up down left right and
then pi
is affordances considered over the given
time Horizon so over one time step depth
so not a deep model
affordances are the same as policies
because it's just the list of
affordances whereas if you were doing
like a depth of three in time
then
you would have
affordances to the third power that
number
um
how are
policies evaluated
using free energy calculations how are
policies selected free energy
minimization what does that look like in
code here's the active inference Loop
the heart of the octave inference Loop
is
inference on States
that is taking in observations
and doing hidden State inference
then inference on policy
what am I updating my policy posterior
to be
and then sampling from your policy
posterior
this is like observe and Orient
this is like decide and act
but what pi mdp has done an incredible
job of
is making it so that the a b c d are
defined you have to Define what those
are here's how C is defined
and then you define an agent
as a b c and d my agent
a is a b is b c is c d is d
we Define the agent that's the
generative model
we Define the environment that's the
generative process
and then we write the loop
that connects the generative model and
the generative process
Giuseppe
yes uh so you you talked about the E
Matrix and you called it the Matrix of
affordances
um
I think I remember in the book it was it
was more like the habits was it is it
correct
yes this is the same thing yes so
um affordance I I you know I'm thinking
about uh gibsonian uh affordances but
is it this I maybe I don't see the links
uh
all right great I'm gonna go for um
a short answer and then a more
um something that connects us to some
ongoing debates in the area
the E Matrix both describes the
affordances in terms of the action
possibilities as well as to what extent
they're habitual and so like let's just
say that there's four um we can go up
down left right
so if there's um a one one one one for
up down left right that's like saying
you can go up down left right and
they're all equally likely to happen
if it were like one one one nine
then it's like you can go up down left
right but this one has a higher prior
probability on policy
if this were like one one zero nine it's
like this cannot happen as well as
things that aren't listed can't happen
so the E Matrix
describes action possibilities
and by doing so
whatever is included in the list is an
is at least there is a prior on that
action happening
and then quantitatively the value of the
E Matrix describes the habitualness and
then like in chapter five
we saw about how like dopamine
mediates or is modeled to mediate
the handoff
between more habit-guided
here habit just gets passed through
actions are selected more based upon
what one has already acted upon in the
past whereas here we can see free energy
evaluation
as sharpening your policy prior
into a policy posterior that you then
sample from
come on so free energy minimization is
then like kind of like that type 2
Thinking where we're sharpening our
policy distribution so that we can make
a decision that has a lower expected
free energy
even if that's not the one that we would
have gone to from habit and then just to
connect it to um some recent
um discussions I'll put this in the chat
so request um access if if you want on
the gibsonian note there is this paper
um trick or treat and long story long
story but there is like a Markov blanket
trick paper by these authors and then a
bunch of commentaries
and then just a few days ago they made a
comeback
summarizing the commentaries and going
further and
um
basically their
main issue is
the fep affordance concept isn't the
gibsonian affordance direct perception
of action possibilities concept
ergo
read the paper to find out more but we
had very fun discussions and it spoke
exactly to the gibsonian question
okay well thank you very very clear
thank you awesome
okay in our last just like few minutes
any other notes
awesome so um
we're gonna be
in chapter six for the next two weeks
chapter six is not that long
um
so this will be a good
time
to
make
this process of active modeling
our own
and customize it
provide templates
connect it to the work that's already
happening in pi mdp
explore ways that we can
go from
vision of the scenarios that people want
to model
into
the kinds of models that will have
pragmatic and epistemic value for us
any last comments or I will close the
recording
quick question uh because I haven't I
haven't watched the the p y p y MVP uh
talk yet but is a like all the codes
that are in the in the book are actually
been reward are reworked and are
available in in Python
no that is not the case yet but with
some automated and semi-automated work
it could be
um in model stream 7.2 which you can
find from live streams
um in the video description is that is
this notebook
so
um but we don't have um notebooks for
the Matlab code let alone python trans
uh formations but if somebody wants to
do that
let's do that
okay thank you yep and in the code
page
there's there's a GitHub repo
so if some it just if somebody
wants to add the code just
feel free
all right so see you
um cohort too thanks for continuing on
see you future weeks at this time and
also there's the optional like in like
eight or ten hours or something like the
Discord office hours we'll just chill
and um
just there will be people from different
cohorts
and we'll just
go where people want to go so thank you
feel free to stay on for um cohort 2
beginning in just a minute all right
thank you thank you